Guide to the Records of the Office of the Chancellor and Executive Vice President: David D. Henry and Carroll V. Newsom, John E. Ivey, Jr., George D. Stoddard, and Russell D. Niles 1942-1966 (Bulk 1952-1956) RG 6.0
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the Chancellor and Executive Vice President (David D. Henry and Carroll V. Newsom, John E. Ivey, Jr., George D. Stoddard, and Russell D. Niles)
Bulk, 1952-1956
1942-1966
RG 6.0
New York University Archives
38.5 linear feet 72 manuscript boxes
This collection contains the administrative records of the Chancellor and Executive Vice President at NYU from 1952-1966: David Dodds Henry (1952-1955) and Carroll Vincent Newsom (1955-1956); John Eli Ivey, Jr., (1957-1959); George Dinsmore Stoddard (1960-1964); and Russell Denison Niles (1964-1966).
New York University. Office of the Chancellor and Executive Vice President.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject.
The files are grouped into 5 series:
I, David D. Henry/Carroll V. Newsom
II, John E. Ivey, Jr.
III, George D. Stoddard
IV, Russell D. Niles
V, Additional Accession
Separated Material
Former Series I, Subseries B: Educational Television has been removed and described in its own finding aid:
Guide to the Records of the Educational Television Subseries of the Office of the Executive Vice-Chancellor, Administrations of David D. Henry and Carroll Newsom 1952-1956 RG 3.1
Related Material at the New York University Archives
Records of the Edwin Berry Burgum Academic Freedom Case, 1934-1961
Administrative Papers of Chancellor/Executive Vice President Sidney Borowitz, 1967-1977
Newsom, Carroll, Personal Papers, 1924-1986
Scope and Content Note
The administrative records of the Office of the Chancellor and Executive Vice President span the years 1952-1966. The records were processed in ten different segments for the purpose of student assignments. The material has now been merged into one cohesive collection, and access is provided by this guide. The records consist of correspondence, circular memoranda, minutes, reports, meeting notes, policy statements and analyses, evaluations, press releases, printed material, newspaper clippings, surveys and questionnaires, and a few photographs. Original order - alphabetical in most instances - has been maintained, and the series generally reflect the manner in which the documents were originally filed. Folder contents have been arranged chronologically.
The collection has been divided into five subgroups, representing each of the Chancellor and Executive Vice Presidents, with the exception of David Henry and Carroll Newsom, who have been combined into one subgroup due to the paucity of the Newsom material and an inability, in some cases, to differentiate between tenures (see series note below). In addition, a small portion of records generated in the final months of the George Stoddard administration were originally interfiled with the bulk of the Russell Niles' papers and have been maintained that way for reasons of continuity and logic (see series note below). Within each subgroup the material has been further divided into series and subseries according to original order. Series titles generally reflect the original file titles and have been changed only when it was necessary to highlight a particular grouping and facilitate access without disturbing the inherent arrangement.
The last series, Additional Accession, contains records from all five C/EVPs. Within each subgroup the material has been further divided into series and subseries according to original order. Series titles generally reflect the original file titles and have been changed only when it was necessary to highlight a particular grouping and facilitate access without disturbing the inherent arrangement.
The adminstrative records of Henry and Newsom span the years 1942-1964, with the bulk of the material created from 1952-1956. The scant number of records attributed to Newsom suggest that he took many of his files with him upon being elected President of NYU in 1956, leaving records that were indistinct or closely linked to the files of Henry, as in the case of the educational television series. The records of Henry contain some gaps as well; not all files seem to cover his full term in office.
Historical/Biographical Note
Upon taking office in 1951, Chancellor Henry T. Heald began to centralize administrative functions. He found the administration's history of making decisions based on budgetary demands to be at odds with the goals of an institution for higher learning. Heald sought to develop a policy emphasizing essential educational objectives at a time when the University's rapid growth threatened academic development. In order to preserve the accomplishments achieved through expansion and at the same time execute greater control over educational policy, Heald bolstered the ranks of the central administration by appointing in 1952 David D. Henry to the newly created position of Executive Vice Chancellor. Henry assumed the duties of the discontinued Office of the Provost and served as the chief educational officer of the university. Shortly thereafter, Heald appointed an assistant to the Executive Vice Chancellor for University Development.
The grant-funded New York University Self-Study Plan, an exhaustive analysis of NYU's policies and practices, outlined a new administrative organization as part of a comprehensive, long-range plan. In affirming centralized authority, the self-study prompted the revision of executive titles: the Chancellor became the President, Vice Chancellors became Vice Presidents, and the University Council became the Board of Trustees.
In 1960, the Board of Trustees amended the bylaws to change the title of the Executive Vice President to Chancellor and Executive Vice President (C/EVP). Although the new title did not bring with it a change in duties, it more accurately reflected the C/EVP's position as second in command, while indicating that the Office of the C/EVP was endowed with NYU's original conception of the Chancellor: the head of faculty, the chief liaison between faculty, students, and Board of Trustees, and the officer to recommend faculty.
The C/EVP served as the academic alter ego of the President. As chief of University Operations, the C/EVP supervised schools and divisions, student housing, special programs, relations with the State and Federal Departments of Education, and training programs like the now defunct ROTC. The C/EVP was in charge of most "internal organizational problems," and also attended to related educational activities outside the immediate needs of the university, such as educational television and various research projects. In addition, the C/EVP oversaw the Academic Council (later changed to the Dean's Council, then the Committee of Deans), a small advisory group resulting from a self-study recommendation and consisting of high ranking officers who are each "responsible for a major segment of the university's educational program, as to policy and administration." In addition, the Office of Institutional Research and Educational Planning operated until 1975, under the authority of the C/EVP. The C/EVP office was dissolved in 1977.
David Dodds Henry, 1952-1955
David Dodds Henry was named the first Executive Vice Chancellor of NYU in September 1952. During his tenure he served as chairperson of the Metropolitan New York Educational Agencies Committee on Television, and two other committees on educational television, sponsored by the American Council on Education. In addition, he was a member of the Special Committee for Rubber Research of the National Science Foundation, and a member of the National Planning Association. Henry frequently lectured on educational television, the use of computers in education, and the university in an urban environment. In 1955 Henry left NYU to assume the presidency of the University of Illinois.
Carroll Vincent Newsom, 1955-1956
In July 1955, Carroll Newsom was appointed to succeed David Henry. Newsom brought a distinguished career as a mathematics professor and administrator to NYU. He was subsequently elected president of the University at the time of Henry Heald's resignation in September 1956. Newsom resigned as President in September 1961 and became a senior Vice President at Prentice Hall Publishers.
John Eli Ivey, Jr., 1957-1959
John Ivey, formerly a sociologist at the University of North Carolina, was appointed Executive Vice President of NYU in March 1957. Ivey supported many special projects and exploratory programs at NYU, expanding his position and the scope of the central administration. He resigned in September 1959 and later became Dean of the College of Education and Professor of Sociology at Michigan State University.
George Dinsmore Stoddard, 1960-1964
George Stoddard, a psychologist and former president of the University of Illinois, came to NYU in 1953 after diplomatic service with the post-war educational mission to Japan. Before becoming Chancellor and Executive Vice President in January 1960, Stoddard directed the NYU Self-Study and served as Dean of the School of Education. He played a central role in constructing a new hierarchy of administrative offices that centralized educational policy and budgetary control. In 1964, Stoddard resigned to become Distinguished Professor of Education.
Russell Denison Niles, 1964-1966
Russell Niles' long association with NYU began in 1929, when he joined the University as an assistant law professor. He became Dean of the School of Law in 1948, and was named Chancellor and Executive Vice President in February 1964. He resigned in 1966 to become President of the Bar of the City of New York. Niles continued many of the policies of Stoddard, and was an important influence in helping to further centralize and strengthen the administration.
Sources:
Barrett, Ellen. "Inventory of the Records of John E.Ivey, Jr., 1957-1959," NYU Archives, 1981.
Cricco, Nancy. "Inventory to the Records of the George E. Stoddard and Russell D. Niles Administrations, 1963-1965," NYU Archives, 1988.
Sabol, Maria. "Inventory to the Records of David D. Henry, 1952-1956," NYU Archives, 1981.
Still, Bayrd. "Evolution of Organization of General Administrative Offices, 1880-1978," NYU Archives, 1978.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
Please contact the University Archivists with specific questions regarding restrictions.
This collection is in
off-site storage
.
Burgum, Edwin Berry, b. 1894; Heald, Henry T., (Henry Townly), 1904-1975; Henry, David Dodds, 1905-; Ivey, John E., (John Eli), 1919-; New York University |x Faculty |y 20th century.; New York University. College of Medicine.; New York University. Faculty of Arts and Science.; New York University. Finance Office.; New York University. Graduate School of Arts and Science.; New York University. School of Applied Science.; New York University. School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance.; New York University. School of Education.; New York University. School of Engineering and Science.; New York University. School of Medicine.; New York University. Trustees.; Newsom, Carroll Vincent, 1904-; Niles, Russell D., (Russell Denison), 1902-; Stoddard, George Dinsmore, 1897-1981; Washington Square College of Arts and Science.; Administrative records.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Minutes.; New York (N.Y.) |x History |v Sources.; Official Reports.; Press releases.; Reports.; Speeches.; Universities and colleges |x Administration.; Universities and colleges |x Curricula.; Universities and colleges |x Finance.; Universities and colleges |x Professional education.
- Series I: David D. Henry/Carroll V. Newsom
  Scope and Contents note
  The administrative records of David D. Henry and Carroll V. Newsom span the years 1948-1956, with the bulk of the material having been created between 1952-1956. The subgroup measures approximately 6.3 linear feet; 5 linear inches remain from Newsom's tenure. The scant number of records attributed to Newsom suggest that he took many of his files with him upon being elected President of the University in 1956, leaving records that were indistinct or closely linked to the files of David Henry, as in the case of the educational television series. The records of David Henry contain some gaps as well; not all files seem to cover his full term in office. The material has been split into 3 series: administrative; educational television; and speeches and biographical information (Henry only).
  - Subseries A: Administrative
    Records in the administrative subseries consist primarily of correspondence that lends insight into Henry's and Newsom's interaction with the University community, particularly Henry's strong relationships with other administrators, including President Henry Heald. The series contains information on the Edwin Berry Burgum case, the English Professor who was dismissed as a result of a House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) investigation of his alleged membership in the communist party (Box 1/Fldrs. 5-6), and College of Medicine Professor Albert Keston's attempt to seek draft deferment on the grounds that he was performing valuable research (Box 6/Fldrs. 15-16). In addition, the files contain information on land acquisitions (Box 6/Fldr. 5), substantial material on the expansion of the NYU Medical Center (Box 7/Fldrs. 49), and correspondence regarding the American Korean Foundation and American benefits to Korean War veterans (Box 1/Fldrs. 1-2; Box 8/ Fldr 1).
    - American Korean Foundation, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General note
      bar code: 3 1142 04225475 8
    - American Korean Foundation, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      bar code: 3 1142 042254758
    - Armsey, James W., 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Association of College Honor Societies, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Burgum, E. Berry, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Burgum, E. Berry, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Commerce, School of, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Commerce, School of, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Commerce, School of, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Commerce, School of, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Commerce, School of, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      bar code: 3 1142 042254766
    - Commerce, School of - Special Anniversary Committee to Select New Dean, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Deans and Directors, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Deans and Directors, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Dentistry, College of, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Dentistry, College of, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Dentistry, College of, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Dentistry, College of - Appointment of Dean Nagle, Raymond J., 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Dentistry, College of - Deanship, Candidates for, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      bar code: 3 1142 042254774
    - Education, School of, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Education, School of, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Education, School of, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Education, School of, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Education, School of, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Education, School of, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      bar code: 3 1142 042254782
    - Education, School of, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Education, School of - Dean, Committee for the Selection of, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Engineering, College of, 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Engineering, College of, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Engineering, College of, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Engineering, College of, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Engineering, College of, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Engineering, College of, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Engineering, College of, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Engineering, College of, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Engineering, College of - Report for Engineers Council on Professional Development, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      bar code: 3 1142 042254790
    - General Education, Division of, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - General Education, Division of, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - General Education, Division of, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - General Education, Division of, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Graduate School of Arts & Science, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Graduate School of Arts & Science, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Graduate School of Business Administration, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Graduate School of Business Administration, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      bar code: 3 1142 042254808
    - Graduate School of Business Administration, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Graduate School of Public Administration and Social Service, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Graduate School of Public Administration and Social Service, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Heald, Henry T. - Chancellor, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Heald, Henry T. - Chancellor, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Howley, Frank L. - Vice Chancellor, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Howley, Frank L. - Vice Chancellor, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Institute of Fine Arts, 1952-1954 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Institute of Fine Arts, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Judson Student Center, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Kastner, Elwood C. - Registrar and Dean of Admission, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Kastner, Elwood C. - Registrar and Dean of Admission, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Keller, Herbert B. - Mathematics Research Group, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Keston, Albert S. - Assistant Professor, College of Medicine, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Keston, Albert S. - Assistant Professor, College of Medicine, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Kimball, Leroy E. - Vice Chancellor and Comptroller, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Law, School of, 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      bar code: 3 1142 042254816
    - Law, School of, 1953-1955 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Libraries, 1952-1954 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Medical Center, 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Medical Center, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Medical Center, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Medical Center, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Medicine, College of, 1952-1955 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Medicine, College of, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Research Service, Office of, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      bar code: 3 1142 042254824
    - Retailing, School of, 1952-1955 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Richards, John R. - Director of Research Service, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Smith, Rufus - Provost, 1951-1954 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - University College, 1952-1954 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - University College, 1954-1955 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - University Physician, Office of, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Voorhis, Harold O. - Vice Chancellor and Secretary, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Voorhis, Harold O. - Vice Chancellor and Secretary, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Washington Square College, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Washington Square College, 1953-1954 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Washington Square College, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Washington Square College, 1954-1955 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Separation Folder, 0000 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Subseries B: Speeches and Biographical Material
    The third series in this subgroup represents the public side of David Henry during the years 1952-1955, with one file containing material as far back as 1949. Henry made frequent speaking engagements and public appearances to promote his interests in educational strategies and techniques such as the use of film, television and computers, along with foreign exchange and urban outreach programs. NYU dedications, and speeches to NYU associations and councils are also included. The series measures .5 linear feet.
    - Biographical Material, 1952-1955 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      bar code: 3 1142 042254832
    - Speeches, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Speeches, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Speeches, 1954-1955 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Speeches, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Speeches, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Speeches, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Speeches, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      bar code: 3 1142 042254840
    - Speeches, 19531954 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Speeches, 1952- 1953 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Speeches (before arrival at NYU), 1949-1952 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Series II: John E. Ivey, Jr.
  The records of John E. Ivey Jr. measure approximately 6.3 linear feet. The bulk of the material spans the years 1957-1959, with some files dating back to 1954. This subgroup has been processed into one administrative series containing 17 subseries. Certain files covering student problems, faculty appointments and the selection of Deans are restricted.
  The records exhibit many of the changes occurring at NYU during this period, such as the introduction of all university departments, a point of contention between the administration and the Deans (see subseries III & XV), and an increased awareness of international affairs during the height of the Cold War. A subseries on international affairs (XII) contains material on the Center for International Affairs, the Brazilian Institute, Israel and a ground breaking Soviet-U.S. engineering exchange program.
  The volume of records pertaining to international affairs is just one example of Ivey's more extraverted approach to NYU's educational mission than that of his predecessors. The files reflect a continuing involvement in educational television (subseries XVIII), while demonstrating the emergence of other technological advances in the field of education, such as the language laboratory and improved computer facilities. In addition, a subseries on special projects (XVI) conveys the sense of a new creative spirit at NYU during the late 1950s and leading into the early 1960s. There are files on various arts groups, an experimental liberal arts program, atomic energy, and many research ventures, programs and proposals. Finally, a file on the American Association of University Professors contains further information on the case of Edwin Berry Burgum, the Professor dismissed for being a member of the Communist Party.
  - Subseries A: Administration
    - Business Office, 1957-1958 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      bar code: 3 1142 042254857
    - Business Office, 1958-1959 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - By-Laws and Charter Faculty Handbook, 1955-1958 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Educational Services, Office of, 1958-1959 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Executive Vice-President - Manual of Functions and Responsibilities, 1958-1959 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Institutional Research, Office of - John Dale Russell, 1958-1959 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - institutional Research, Office of, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Long Range Study and Planning, 1956-1958 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Long Range Study and Planning, 1958-1959 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - President, Office of - Carrol V. Newsom, 1958-1959 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Summer Session, Director of, 1957-1959 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      bar code: 3 1142 042254865
    - Vice-President and Secretary, Office of - Harold O. Voorhis, 1958-1959 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Subseries B: Admissions
    - Admissions Office, 1957-1959 (Box 12, Folder 3)